Thank you for being here this weekend and being part of this Donna Weekend, the heart of which will take place tomorrow.
And our teachers for the weekend will be arriving tomorrow in buses from all over the county.
And I'd like to take this opportunity tonight to clarify a little bit about what Donna really is.
We translate it as giving, but giving doesn't reach it at all.
And we have that problem with the English language and translating some of these Buddhist terms into English because the English versions of them, the closest English word to them, has totally different meanings.
And as a result, they become misinterpreted.
And that's why many of them we retain in the original form, such as Donna.
Donna is one of the paramitas.
There are six paramitas.
And these paramitas have been in existence a long time.
They're part of Mahayana Buddhism, which Zen is a part of.
And Donna is the first of those.
And each one of the paramitas, when you try to translate them, you somehow miss what they're about.
For example, we translate Prajna paramita.
Paramita literally means other shore or to cross over.
And our way of understanding crossing over to the other shore in Zen is that the other shore arrives, or indeed, that the other shore is right here, right now.
Prajna, we translate as wisdom.
And wisdom, if you look it up in a dictionary, talks about accumulating knowledge.
It's not what Prajna means.
It has nothing to do with knowledge, nor does it have anything to do with knowing.
So that the calling it wisdom misses it.
The same with the word Karuna, we translate as compassion.
Compassion has a sense of empathy about it, which implies self and other.
In compassion, there is no dualism.
There is no self or other.
And we translate dana as giving.
And that, too, misses the point.
Because giving is not dana.
Not quite dana.
There can be no dana, unless there is both giving and receiving occurring simultaneously.
So that the giver and the receiver are unified.
They become one thing.
It's the same with compassion.
There's no doer or the thing that you're doing to.
There's no effort or even sense of it occurring.
Compassion happens the way your hair grows.
It's spontaneous.
There's no knowledge of it.
So dana is not charity.
And it's not generosity.
And it's not almsgiving or donation or beneficence or benevolence or benefaction.
It's not contribution or gift or philanthropy or offering.
But rather, it's the practice of total, unequivocal relinquishment.
What is relinquishment?
What does that mean?
The great master, Hui Hai, who was a successor of Basso, talked about it in a dialogue with one of his monks.
The monk asked, by what means can the gateway of our school be entered?
The master said, by means of dana paramita.
According to the Buddha and the Bodhisattva path, the monk said,
the Bodhisattva path consists of six paramitas.
Why then have you mentioned only one?
Please explain why this one alone provides a sufficient means for us to enter.
The master said, deluded people fail to understand that the other five all proceed from dana paramita
and that it's by practice, by its practice, that all others are fulfilled.
Why it's the first one of the paramitas.
Why is it called dana paramita?
The answer, dana means relinquishment.
Question, relinquishment of what?
Answer, relinquishment of dualism of opposites.
What does that mean?
The monk asked.
It means total relinquishment of ideas as to the dual nature of good and bad,
being and non-being, love and aversion, void and non-void,
concentration and distraction, pure and impure.
By giving all of them up, we attain to a state in which all opposites are seen as empty.
The real practice of dana paramita entails achieving this state without any thought of,
now I see that opposites are void, or now I have relinquished all of them.
We may also call it the simultaneous cutting off of the myriad types of current cause.
For it is when these are cut off that the whole dharma nature becomes void, empty.
And this emptiness of the dharma nature means the non-dwelling of the mind upon anything whatsoever.
Once that state is achieved, not a single form can be discerned.
Why?
Because our self-nature is non-existent and does not contain a single thing foreign to itself.
That which contains no single thing is true reality, the marvelous form of the Tathagatha.
It's said in the Diamond Sutra,
those who relinquish all forms are called Buddhas, or enlightened ones.
So basically what he's saying is that dana is about forgetting the self.
When there's no self, there's no other.
This is the diamond net of Indra, where all things are interconnected,
where all things are codependent,
where all things nourish each other and themselves.
Who forget the self is body and mind fallen away.
In our practice, giving and receiving is at the heart of almost everything that we do.
That's what our service is about.
Our liturgy is about.
We receive the teachings and we return gratitude.
We receive food and we acknowledge.
Therefore, we eat this food with everyone.
We eat to stop all evil, to practice good.
What's the next line?
Save all sentient beings and to accomplish the Buddha way.
So the receiving of the food, it's taken with the intent of giving, to follow it.
We receive the teachings and we give.
We return it.
So giving and receiving, the heart of that in Japanese Buddhism,
they have the practice of takahatsu.
And there they try to recreate that practice of giving and receiving,
where the monk begs for food and receives food
and then gives a chance something for the person that's given them the food.
And it's in that giving and receiving that these two people are unified.
So the giving and receiving is constantly a manifestation of the interrelatedness,
codependency, mutual causality of the diamond net of Indra,
in which all things, every speck of dust in this vast universe is interrelated,
is codependent, has a mutual causality.
What happens to one thing happens to the totality of it.
Past, present, future.
That diamond net exists in the three dimensions of space
as well as the fourth dimension of time.
It's because that there's both giving and receiving happening simultaneously
that it's never exhausted.
When it's really happening that way, it's never exhausted.
And that's why I've always felt that it's essential to people in the helping professions
to really understand what they're doing.
If they're not receiving while they're giving,
if they're doing something for somebody else,
if they're helping somebody else or saving somebody else,
it's all going in one direction.
If they have not yet understood that they are receiving,
that there's a possibility to be received, to receive something.
There is a mutual nourishment.
There is a mutual healing.
Healer and the healed are both healed in the process.
And when you understand that, you don't exhaust anything.
It's endless, boundless.
When I think back at the teachers that I've known in my time of practice,
I've seen that.
The real teachers have boundless energy, people say.
You know, what's the reservoir?
Where does it come from?
What do they plug into?
Well, they're plugged into the center of the universe itself.
That's where the nourishment comes from.
It's by the giving and receiving happening simultaneously.
Asatani Roshi was 88 years old or 89 years old.
Very, very sick.
Close to the end of his life.
Gaunt, weak, trembling.
He had to be helped by two Jesus to go to this Jukai ceremony.
The last Jukai ceremony that he did the day before he died.
And he couldn't even do his bows.
They helped him to his seat.
His voice was very weak as he introduced the whole thing.
And he offered the incense and began the ceremony.
And a lion appeared.
His voice became strong.
The power of his presence enveloped the entire group of people.
He completed the Jukai ceremony as if he were 30 years old instead of 88 years old.
And then relapsed into his being very weak and helped out of the place and everything.
That Jukai ceremony was filling him with energy.
What he was giving, he was receiving.
The next day, he never got out of bed.
He asked his attendant at one point while she was preparing breakfast to sit him up in bed
so he could sit in a Zazen posture.
When she came back, she found him dead.
Where did that energy come from?
It came from the very process of dhana.
And all of what we do is dhana.
Dogen says,
The self gives the self for the sake of giving the self.
The other gives the other for the sake of giving the other.
Giving is purposeless.
The karmic force of such giving prevails as far as the heavenly world and the human world.
So it's not dhana unless it's non-dual, no separation.
Dogen talks about dhana in terms of loving words,
working for the welfare of all beings,
and identity with others.
And his words are the best way of expressing them.
He says,
Loving speech means that as you meet sentient beings,
you first arouse a sense of compassion in your mind
and treat them with considerate and affectionate words.
Praise the virtuous.
Have compassion on the wicked.
As you take delight in affectionate words,
they will gradually flourish,
and then even those loving words,
which were hitherto unknown and unperceived,
will begin to reveal themselves.
Then he says,
in terms of working for the welfare of all beings,
he said,
Working for the welfare of all beings
means that you contrive ways to benefit
all sentient beings, high and low.
The practice of benefiting others is the total truth.
Hence, it serves both self and other far and wide.
Therefore, serve enemies and friends equally
and assist self and other without discrimination.
If you grasp this truth,
you will see that this is the reason
that even grass and trees,
the wind and water,
are all naturally engaged in the activity
of benefiting others.
And your understanding will certainly serve
others' benefit.
And then he says,
Identity with others.
Identity with others is non-differentiation,
non-duality.
This applies equally to the self and to others.
There is a truth that after the self
assimilates the other to itself,
the self lets itself be assimilated to the other.
This relationship of self and other
is infinitely varied according to the circumstances.
So, what Dogen's talking about,
what dana is directing itself to,
is the heart of being,
the vast net of existence
that we call the diamond net,
the virtue of and harmony
of the universe itself.
This is the nature
of all beings,
of all sentient beings.
It's there.
Each one of us has that
ability, that potential.
but somehow
we cover it.
We cover it by our conditioning.
We cover it by our ideas
and notions.
By our sense,
the illusion of separateness.
There are many ways
to get to that.
And of course,
the heart of
and most important way
to get there is Zazen.
Zazen just peels back
the layers of those conditioning.
That conditioning
and underneath it
in that ground of being
is
the perfection of giving.
It's part of
our human characteristic.
what it means
to be human.
It's part of
what it means
to be alive.
To be part of
this great earth,
all of it
is constantly
giving
and receiving.
Every aspect of it,
every atom,
every molecule.
There would be
no life
if it weren't
for that
giving and receiving,
that codependency.
Even if you
go down to
a molecular
or atomic level,
the relationship
between atoms
that makes a molecule,
that makes water,
is giving
and receiving.
It shares
the electrons.
the protons.
It creates
an entity
by the act
of giving
and receiving.
And so it is
from the molecular
atomic level
to the most
complex organisms,
including the universe
itself.
How can we ignore it?
How can we not
understand
that it's part
of what it means
to be in harmony
with the nature
of things?
The spring breeze
warms the earth
and brings the rain.
The earth offers up
plants and vegetation.
All of the earth's
creatures
breathe
the sweet air
that's produced
by this,
feed on the bounty
that's produced
by this,
and then they return
it to the earth.
Isn't all of that
dana?
giving
and receiving
in unity.
That's what
this weekend
is about.
All of what
I said
are the words
and the ideas
that describe it.
Tomorrow
you will have
an opportunity
to experience
it
yourself,
to practice
it
yourself.
You won't
even
taste it
or get
a glimmering
of it
if there's
any
self-centeredness
involved
in what you
do.
Abandon
the self.
Forget
the self
like you do
in Zazen
and give
freely.
Give yourself
away
freely.
Your heart,
your body,
your labor,
your presence,
your love,
your ear,
whatever
is needed.
And if you
do that,
you'll find
out
what the
Asatani
Roshi
knew
for many,
many years.
You'll find
out for
yourself.
So,
again,
thank you
for your
willingness
willingness to
be here,
to participate
in this
practice of
dana.
What happens
next,
boss?
Oh,
all right.
I didn't
want to,
I was late,
and I'm
sorry I was
late.
I was
busily making
notes and
lost track of
the time.
Yeah,
go ahead.
Any questions?
Peter?
Oh.
Okay.
Be easy on
me,
Peter.
Last time
you chewed
me up.
Is
the
dana dinner
Christmas
people
who don't
have
Christmas
or is
it just
for
dana dinner?
Well,
what does
dana dinner
mean to
you?
When you
say,
or is it
just
dana dinner?
So,
I need to
know what
you mean
by just
dana dinner.
I mean,
is it just
like that?
Is it just
a thing
that's
actually,
I mean,
what I've
been saying,
and let me
say it again
in a little
bit of a
different way,
what it
is for us
as Buddhists
here is
a way to
learn for
ourselves
what the
Buddha was
talking about,
what the
Buddha's
teachings
meant when
they talked
about
dana,
that dana
is an
act of
giving and
receiving at
the same
time.
It's like
when you
stub your
toe,
it needs
help,
and you
immediately
give,
you grab
your foot
and you
hop around
saying,
ooh,
and then
you receive,
you start
feeling better.
You
give the
nourishment,
you know,
you stroke
yourself,
and you
receive it
simultaneously.
so that's
what giving
and receiving
dana means
to a
Buddhist.
And
what we
want to
learn this
weekend
is how in
this process
of getting
together with
all these
people
to make
that work.
And if we
can make it
work here,
you know,
being very
aware of it
and conscious
of it,
maybe then
we can
make it
work in
the world.
So it's
not the
same as
walking along
and there's
some poor
guy on the
side of the
road that
says,
do you
have a
quarter for
a cup of
coffee?
And you
say,
sure,
here.
And they
say,
oh,
thank you
very much.
You say,
it's okay.
And they
go have a
cup of
coffee.
That's
charity.
So it's
not charity.
You know,
it's not
being a
benefactor.
It's not
making
yourself
higher,
bigger,
or more
important.
See,
when you
help somebody,
usually that
person is
down and
out and
you're
bigger and
stronger.
Donna makes
you the
same and
then completely
merged into
one thing.
So there's
only Peter
in the whole
universe.
He's swallowed
up everything.
Okay?
Anyone else?
Why do we do
it at Christmas?
We're actually,
I mean,
Christmas,
that holiday
time is,
I mean,
so obviously
universal.
You know,
they even make
a big deal
out of it in
Japan now.
And as time
goes on and
the earth
gets smaller,
all the
countries are
doing it,
even without
any relationship
to Christmas.
what they've
imported is
the worst
of what
the whole
thing is
about.
I mean,
the whole
concept of
Christ and
Christianity,
and it's the
Catholic Church's
fault for
doing that.
Christ wasn't
born in
December.
He was born
in March.
He's a
Pisces.
I have it
from,
yeah,
he was.
I knew he
wasn't a
Capricorn.
Right.
I mean,
most of the,
Buddha was a
Pisces too.
Gurjeev,
I mean,
a lot of
people,
spiritual
people.
so what's
happened is
what happened
is that
the Druids
had this
pagan holiday
which all
the things
that we
call Christmas
that people
know as
Christmas,
giving of
gifts,
the mistletoe,
the office
party,
getting
drunk,
all those
things were
part of
that
feast
of the
Druids
and people
continued to
do it
and so
the Catholic
Church
moved the
holiday
to that
time
hoping to
overcome it
with the
force of
the birth of
Christ and so
on but what
happened is
they merged
and became
a kind of
a mixture
of both.
Same thing
with Halloween.
Halloween,
I was reading
a thing,
I don't know
how true it
is,
it was put
out by the
born again
Christians,
how evil
Halloween is
and that
it's really
devil worshippers
and so on
and they
traced the
holiday back
also to a
Druid thing
and it had
to do with
the rising
of the dead
and the
worship of
demons
and stuff
like that
and there
was a lot
more to it
and they
made that
Hallow Eve
All Saints
Day
and that
too
ended up
kind of
a merge
thing.
So what
I'd like to
see us do
with that
same thing
and actually
we do this
close to the
solstice,
the winter
I mean clearly
solstice is a
time for
celebration.
All cultures
celebrate the
various solstice
holidays and
equinoxes
because there
are times of
transition
and here
the solstice,
the days will
begin to get
longer and
the approach
of spring
is a cause
for celebration
and my
problem with
it is that
it has become
so awful
to go down
to the mall
and to see
the looks on
people's faces
they're in pain
they're in agony
and then to see
what happens
with the gifts
it's a gesture
it's not really
even giving
not even in the
remotest thing
for the most
part
and I'd like
to see what
the garbage
dumps look like
a week after
Christmas
with all the
things that get
thrown away
and all the
waste that's
created because
of it
and we're just
as bad
I mean we're
not much
better
but I'm
hoping this
year is where
it really struck
me that we
need to do
something to
make it a
little bit
more in
line with
what our
understanding
of Dana
is
in the
same way
that you
know you
can't
you can't
beat
the forces
of the
universe
by just
opposing them
you can't
just throw
up a barrier
so for
example
the media
has done
some awful
stuff
I mean the
reason there
is home
video
and interactive
CD-ROM
is because
of pornography
that's what
if it wasn't
for pornography
those things
never would
have been
born
that's the
multi-billion
dollar industry
that's underneath
it
so what do
you do
you say
okay
we won't
use CD-ROMs
and we'll
never look
at a video
that's not
the answer
to it
the media
is neutral
it's the
artists and
the people
that put it
together
that make
it what
it is
you know
it's like
condemning
cotton
or
metal
because it's
made into
a gun
how can we
use these
things in
a way that
nourishes
rather than
poisons
photography
is a
wonderful
media
it poisons
but it also
nourishes
and it
heals
depends on
how you
use it
so I
think it's
the same
with a lot
of things
in our
society
they're not
going to
go away
so how
can we
use them
to nourish
and that's
basically what
we're exploring
with this
holiday
everybody's
already into
the holiday
and they're
going to do
it one way
or another
and the
people that
can't do
it
because of
circumstances
because they
don't have
the luxury
of choice
like we
have
become
despondent
and disturbed
by it
by not
having that
so this is
an opportunity
to do
something there
but to do
something in a
nourishing way
more positive
way
I think you
do
I've told
a lot of
my students
here the
story of
when I
first started
teaching
it was very
difficult for
me to have
what's called
an anja
an attendant
that takes
care of
the teacher
the reason
it was
difficult for
me is that
my father
died when I
was very
young
and we
were pretty
well all
family
and he
was a
politician
at the
state level
and my
mother was
you know
hostess to
all these
important people
and everything
and then he
died
didn't believe
in insurance
you know
this was
and so he
left us
basically
penniless
my mother
had to go
to work
but she
really didn't
have any
skills
women in
those days
didn't
and so
she went
to school
and worked
and was
cleaning house
and avoiding
I mean she
was just too
proud to
take what
was called
relief
same as
welfare
now she
would never
take it
but I
would find
her crying
at night
because she
was cleaning
houses for
the people
that she
was the
hostess for
years before
you know
she was a
housekeeper
and it
really bothered
me that
I mean it
imprinted me
pretty deeply
I was nine
years old
later when I
got married
and was
making a
lot of
money
my wife
wanted a
housekeeper
and somebody
would come in
and actually
even cook for
us and I
kept resisting
it and then
finally I
agreed to
do it
and we'd
have this
woman come
in who
cleaned the
house and
would feed
the kids
and then
serve us
in another
room I
felt so
awful you
know I
kept thinking
of my
mother just
couldn't do
it you know
and so we
finally stopped
that big
arguments over
it so years
later I
become a
teacher and
part of being
a teacher is
you have a
group of
attendants a
personal
attendant a
secretary a
housekeeper and
all that but
I wasn't going to
do that
and so one
day my
teacher was
visiting me
and we're
at the
house and
I'm running
around serving
him cooking
getting his
ready he
says I
don't want
you to have
your Anja do
that and I
had been his
Anja and I
G ship so I
knew how to do
it so I said
no I don't have
an Anja proudly
a little bit of
pride no I
don't have an
Anja I'm a
regular guy he
said how can
you be so
selfish
I said why
he said what
do you mean
he said how
can you be so
selfish and not
allow your
students to
serve you to
give back to
you what you
give to them
and it changed
my whole notion
about that
and I suddenly
started doing
it I'm still
uncomfortable with
it but I
feel it's an
important part of
the whole process
that they need
to otherwise
they become
thieves they
take and
don't give
and they
feel awful
about it
they want
to
students want
to give
back
I know I
did when I
was serving
my teacher
I felt great
but we used
to fight
over who
could do
it
what about
if you're
on the end
of wanting
to give
back
say that
again
are you
stuck
not
having
Donna
if the
other person
doesn't give
back
or is there
something
that you
can
oh no
they don't
it's not
there's no
conscious giving
on their part
there's no
conscious
I mean
Lenny
mentioned
last night
when we were
at the prison
and I
mentioned it
before
every time
we go to
the prison
to work
with the
prisoners
you know
we're like
the heroes
we come in
from the
outside
and we're
doing something
for them
we're bringing
the Dharma
to them
and everything
and by the
time we're
finished
we're all
walking away
with our
tails between
our legs
because we've
received so much
it seems so
lopsided
you know
and it's not
it's not
that physically
they're saying
okay
you gave me
this now
I'm going
to give
you this
it's just
that it
happens
by the
it's like
making love
you know
nobody's
thinking about
okay you
kiss me
and I'll
kiss you
and you
touch me
I'll
touch you
you know
you just
do it
the birds
and the bees
do it
anybody else
well you
practice that
the way you
practice
you know
your breath
so it
comes up
any thought
I'm good
I'm bad
I'm Santa
Claus
you acknowledge
it throw it
away
come back
to the
moment
I mean
it's
when I
say
nourishment
to be
nourished
it's kind
of a
vague
intangible
term
but I've
talked about
nourishment
in terms
of photography
for example
or in
terms of
art
or music
there is
art
that poisons
and there's
art that
nourishes
poisons
is art
that when
you've
experienced
it
a photograph
a painting
piece of
music
and then
walk away
from it
you feel
as if
you've
lost
something
has
been taken
away
art that
nourishes
when you
walk away
from it
you feel
that you've
received
something
you feel
nicer
better
greater
so
nourishment
is what
I hope
spiritual
nourishment
to take
away
as well
as some
pretty good
food
I mean
those turkeys
are nothing
to scoff
at
you're the
last one
Peter
you started
and you're
going to
close it
go ahead
say that
last line
again
you gave
thanks to
her
what doesn't
make any
well the
best one
to talk
to about
that I
guess is
guess who
I mean I'm
a father
and I
feel good
when my
kids feel
good
so whenever
I can do
something to
help my
kids
I mean
they're all
you would
think they
were old
people
now
you know
they're like
39 years
old
but even
now I
mean I
when I
see that
they're
happy
I'm
my mother
used to
say that
to me
you know
when I
would do
all the
crazy things
that I've
done in
my life
like become
a Zen
Buddhist
my mother's
a Catholic
you know
I'm a Zen
Buddhist
monk
and she
said well
what's a Zen
Buddhist
monk
I said well
you know
it's this
and that
what do
you do
they pay
you
nothing
where do
you
you know
and she
said
and then
it all
would end
with
well
if it
makes you
happy
son
it makes
me happy
and she
really meant
it
you know
so
that's the
way parents
are
pretty weird
you'll find
out one of
these days
I hope
thank you
oh go ahead
one more
really
for
make believe
I have
another age
my 65
age
is the one
that
technically
I am
that
is
I'm a
Pisces
I was born
in February
but my
real age
I'm a
Gemini
and I
was born
in 1931
so
I have
two ages
I think
so
as far
as I'm
concerned
they weren't
thank you
everybody